<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at St. Olave Southwark, September the 8th, 1700 occasioned by the recantation of Dr. Joh. Spire, lately a Quaker : which said recantation is added at the end / by John Haslewood ...</title>
            <author>Haslewood, John, b. 1647.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1132</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14553</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13142526</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13142526</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97998</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43071)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97998)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 420:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at St. Olave Southwark, September the 8th, 1700 occasioned by the recantation of Dr. Joh. Spire, lately a Quaker : which said recantation is added at the end / by John Haslewood ...</title>
                  <author>Haslewood, John, b. 1647.</author>
                  <author>Spire, John. Oration at the parish-church of St. Olave-Southwark.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Abel Roper ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Spire, John.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Isaiah LV, 3 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97998:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at St. <hi>Olave Southwark, September</hi> the 8th, 1700. Occaſioned by the Recanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Dr. <hi>Joh. Spire,</hi> lately a Quaker; Which ſaid Recantation is added at the end.</p>
            <p>By JOHN HASLEWOOD, D. D. Rector of St. <hi>Olave Southwark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the Requeſt of the Perſons concerned, and ſeveral others of that Pariſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Roper</hi> at the <hi>Black Boy</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi> over againſt St. <hi>Dunſtans-Church,</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97998:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97998:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IT is not a trifling deſire of appearing in Print (to which poſſibly I have as great an averſeneſs as any one can conclude from what he ſhall here read, I ought to have) that hath prevailed upon me to publiſh this following Diſcourſe, which labours under a double diſadvantage of being compoſed in haſt, and upon a Text choſen for me, by him at whoſe Requeſt it was Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, but a ſincere endeavour to inform ſome miſtaken honeſt People of the dangerouſneſs of thoſe Principles, which are here laid open, that they may leave them; and to eſtabliſh others who have already left them; to both which purpoſes, ſome who heard it, have been ſo favourable as to think it may be uſeful. But whether it will or no, I muſt leave to your judgments. However ſuch as it is, I offer it up to you, hoping that if it fall ſhort of other Peoples expectations, it may reach my own deſign, which was to be as helpful as I could to any that ſhould need ſuch aſſiſtance. And if by that means I can contribute in the leaſt to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of God's Glory, it is no matter for my own.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:97998:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97998:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Iſaiah 55.3.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Incline your ear, and come unto me; hear, and your Soul ſhall live, and I will make an everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with you, even the ſure mercies of David.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis Chapter is made up of Precepts and Promiſes, for in it God not only makes his will known, and declares after what manner he will have Men to addreſs themſelves to him; but encourageth them to Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience by the aſſurance of a Reward, which though in the Letter it be carnal, yet in its true meaning is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual; for though God promiſeth his People, that upon the forſaking of Idols, he would bring them out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and make them as ſucceſsful as they had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate; that there ſhould be ſuch a change in the face of their Affairs, as ſhould affect even Nature her ſelf, and make an alteration in her; for in the two laſt Verſes it is ſaid, <hi>Ye ſhall go out with joy, and be lead forth with peace: the mountains and the hills ſhall break forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you into ſinging, and all the trees of the field ſhall clap their hands, inſtead of the thorn ſhall come up the firr-tree, and inſtead of the briar ſhall come up the myrtle-tree.</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding theſe expreſſions, which reliſh only of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral ſatisfactions, we are to conceive that ſuch Bleſſings are ſignified by them, as are too high to ſtoop to ſenſe; and a Redemption from <hi>Babylonian</hi> Bondage did intimate a much more glorious deliverance from the captivity of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97998:4"/>Sin, and the power of Hell. So by the <hi>Waters</hi> in the firſt Verſe, we are to underſtand the Grace of God, and the <hi>thirſty</hi> are thoſe who have a lively ſenſe of the want of it, and an eager deſire of a ſupply; who have all the violent cravings after God and Goodneſs, which that appetite is wont to produce towards its proper ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; and when they that have <hi>no Money</hi> are called upon to <hi>buy and eat,</hi> the meaning is that they who could not gain this good of themſelves, might have it <hi>gratis;</hi> for it would be no chargeable thing to them to learn true Doctrine, which is oftentimes compared to Meat and Drink, becauſe it feeds and nouriſheth the Soul; ſo <hi>Jer.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Thy words were found, and I did eat them, and thy word was unto me the joy and rejoycing of my heart;</hi> and Prov. 9.5. <hi>Come eat of my bread, ſaith Wiſdom, and drink of the Wine, which I have mingled;</hi> and in my Text God incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates the ſame thing, which he had urged in the firſt Verſe, and exhorts poor Sinners to embrace Chriſt by a true and lively Faith, together with thoſe unſpeakable precious Benefits which are tendered in him; and for the exciting them to a diligent attention and careful obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to his heavenly Inſtruction, he promiſeth to <hi>make with them an everlaſting Covenant,</hi> not like that which he had made with the <hi>Jews,</hi> which was to endure for a while, and then be abrogated, but ſuch an one as ſhould out-laſt time it ſelf, <hi>even the ſure mercies of David,</hi> i.e. that Mercy which God had promiſed to <hi>David,</hi> that he would give him a Son, who ſhould Reign over his Church and People for ever; which Promiſe was to be fully comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97998:4"/>in Chriſt, who, though he were crucified, yet ſhould he be raiſed again, never to dye any more; for of his Life and Dorninion there ſhould be no end; and for this Expoſition I have St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Authority, who quotes this very Paſſage for a Proof of Chriſt's Reſurrection, at <hi>Acts</hi> 13.34. <hi>And as concerning that be raiſed him up from the dead, now no more to return to corruption, he ſaid on this wiſe, I will give you the ſure mercies of David.</hi> And if <hi>Chriſt, who is the Head of the Body, the Church, be the firſt-born from the dead;</hi> we alſo, who are his Members, if we walk in new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of life, ſhall riſe after him to a glorious and immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table State. <hi>But every Man in his own order, Chriſt the firſt-fruits, and after they that are Chriſt at his coming.</hi> The Words thus explained contain in them theſe two parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Precept, or if you pleaſe you may call it a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Invitation to Mercy, <hi>Incline your ear, and come unto me.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. An Encouragement to obſerve the Precept, or to accept of the Invitation, in theſe words, <hi>and your Soul ſhall live, and I will make an everlaſting covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of David,</hi> i. e. Thoſe who ſerved God faithfully, ſhould be made partakers of a joyful Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. And,</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Precept, or Invitation, <hi>Come unto me,</hi> and here there will be nothing elſe needful then to inquire how we are to come to God, which we muſt do two ways.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. By Faith.</item>
               <item>2. By Repentance.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. We muſt come to God by Faith, <hi>i. e.</hi> We muſt believe all thoſe Truths which he hath revealed in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97998:5"/>more eſpecially that grant fundamental point of belief which is a <hi>Crucified Saviour.</hi> And this was that Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle upon which St. <hi>Paul</hi> reſted, as he told the Church of <hi>Corinth, I determined not to know any thing among you, ſave Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified;</hi> and upon this Confeſſion did our Saviour build his Church, <hi>viz.</hi> upon St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Creed, which was no more than this, <hi>We are ſure that thou art Chriſt, the Son of the living God.</hi> And for the ſake of this Article, were the four Goſpels given us. <hi>For all theſe things are written, that ye might believe that Jeſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God.</hi> And if the Evangeliſts be found to be falſe Witneſſes, it will be as impoſſible to ſupport the veracity and credit of the other Writers of the New Teſtament, as it is to keep up a Superſtructure, after the Foundation is taken away. And the Scripture not only bears Teſtimony to the Article it ſelf, but to all them that acknowledge it. <hi>For every Spirit that confeſſeth that Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is come in the Fleſh, is of God, ſaith St. John; and whoſoever confeſſeth that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in God,</hi> 1 John, 4.2, 15. And then, as for them, who ſet their faces againſt him, who is declared to be the <hi>power and wiſdom of God,</hi> and tell us only of a <hi>Chriſt within;</hi> we may very well allow them to have the Spirit, but it is only that of <hi>lying.</hi> But I would demand of theſe Men, whether or no the <hi>Chriſt within</hi> was crucified, dead and buried at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and roſe again the third day? Whether he was afterwards ſeen by hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of People, and did eat with the Apoſtles, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced them that what they ſaw was a real Body by ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97998:5"/>them his Hands and Feet? All which are expreſly affirmed of our Saviour; and therefore nothing but an infinite clemency could make him ſtill endure ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction of Sinners againſt himſelf. And yet it is the moſt common practiſe imaginable of <hi>Quakers</hi> to contemn and revile all thoſe who ſpeak to them of the coming of <hi>that juſt one, of whom the Jews were the betrayers and the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers,</hi> Acts, 7.52. Nay ſome of them have been ſo prodigiouſly audacious, as to beſpatter him with ſuch foul and contemptuous expreſſions, as I am afraid to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and cannot think of, without extreme horrour and amazement.<note n="*" place="margin">What I here allude to, may be ſeen <hi>in the Snake in the Graſs,</hi> Vol. <hi>1.</hi> Pag. <hi>78.</hi> The Author of which Book 1 know to be a Perſon of too great ſincerity, to affirm any thing poſitively, which he is not ſure of. But if he hath accuſed them wrongfully, it is ſomewhat ſtrange that they ſhould not call him to account for it: I ſuppoſe their fond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of him is no inducement to conceal ſuch a failing.</note> And then wherewithal ſhall they be cleanſed, who thus deſpiſe that Blood, which alone can purify them from their Sins? What Laver will be ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to waſh away this deep ſtain of Infidelity? But Lord! Though they thus blaſpheme the Name of thy Dear Son, grant that we may earneſtly beg, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally obtain the Benefits of his Paſſion, and turn that Curſe of the Jews upon themſelves into a Bleſſing upon us, and <hi>let his Blood be upon us, and our Children, for our good.</hi> But can Faith alone ſave us? Will it be enough to fix our eye upon God? No my Text requireth us to <hi>Incline our ear to him,</hi> to fulfil his holy Will and Commandments,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97998:6"/>or with a truly humble and contrite Heart to implore his Mercy for our manifold Sins and Trangſreſſions. We muſt therefore in the next place come to him by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And this, I ſuppoſe all, <hi>but Quakers,</hi> will grant to be neceſſary to Salvation, that every one muſt either lead a good life, or repent of a bad one. But with them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is a toyl as inſignificant as tedious; there being no need of their contrition, who cannot offend; for why ſhould they afflict their Souls, who are arrived to a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Perfection? Which is an happineſs that theſe morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and humble Creatures lay claim to: And therefore a great Preacher among them, repreſents a <hi>Quaker,</hi> as meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſtronger than <hi>Samſon,</hi> wiſer than <hi>Solomon,</hi> and more patient than <hi>Job.</hi> Nay farther, harmleſs and innocent as Chriſt himſelf.<note n="(a)" place="margin">
                  <hi>W. Shewen</hi>'s Treatiſe concerning Thoughts and Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations, <hi>P. 25.</hi>
               </note> Whatever in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances there may be of humane infirmities, it is beneath a <hi>Quaker</hi> to increaſe the number; for he boaſts of as great a ſecurity from Sin, as the Pſalmiſt promiſed himſelf from bodily evilds: <hi>Tho' a thouſand ſhould fall beſide him, and ten thouſand at his right hand, yet ſhould not wickedneſs. come nigh him;</hi> for amidſt all the Spoils of Sin and Corruption he is reſolved to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main untouched, and in this ſenſe to be <hi>free among the dead.</hi> I grant indeed that Scripture ſeems to favour this Principle, and to allow of a ſtate of unſinning Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, when it affirms ſome to be ſo innocent, as to need no Repentance; but I conceive the meaning of that place to be no more than this, that though they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97998:6"/>the ſtate of Grace, and ſo need not Repentance, as it is a converſion of the whole, yet they do need con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition for their ſingle acts of Sin; for how elſe could the Holy Spirit ſay, <hi>That in many things we offend all?</hi> And why did our Saviour in that abſolute form of Prayer, which he hath appointed, bid us pray to <hi>Our Father which is in Heaven, to forgive us our treſpaſſes?</hi> And let any one but conſult the frailty of his own Nature, and he will find the Diſeaſes of his Soul to be at the leaſt as nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous as thoſe of his Body; that betwixt his ſtrayings and backſlidings the burden of his Sins muſt needs be intole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. And then what way is there for him to obtain any eaſe, but by caſting that weight of his Sins from him? By ſweeping and garniſhing his Soul, not that thoſe evil Spirits, which had been ejected, might return again, or that other more unclean ones might be admitted in their ſtead; but that the Holy Dove, which loves not dark Houſes, might make his abode with him, when he was become a Child of Light. And to this conſideration of our own weakneſs, add we that other no leſs weighty one of the ſubtlety and watchfulneſs of our Enemy; who hath been long practiſed in the arts of treachery and inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation, and knows too well when, and how to ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our affections with the leaſt difficulty and greateſt ſucceſs. Now if we live thus in perpetual dangers, both within and without, how is it poſſible for us to be ſure that we ſhall always eſcape them? that we ſhall neither willfully betray our ſelves, nor fall into our Enemy's hand unawares? That we ſhall neither <hi>run,</hi> nor be <hi>lead</hi> into
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97998:7"/>captivity? He therefore that thinks himſelf above Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, needs it moſt of all; and that very Pride of heart calls for plenty of Tears and Aſhes, for the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſighing, and the humbleſt proſtration. I conclude then, that ſince <hi>in God's ſight no Man living can be juſtified,</hi> the moſt righteous Perſon muſt neceſſarily ſtand in need of Pardon; and the way for him to obtain it, is to plead guilty, that ſo he may avert that Wrath which he had deſerved, and regain that Mercy which he had forfeited. And this brings me to my next Head, <hi>viz.</hi> The encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement that God hath given to all People to <hi>incline their ear, and come unto him,</hi> that he will give them the ſure Mercies of <hi>David,</hi> make them partakers of a joyful Reſurrection.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But if this be the certain reward of true Faith and Repentance, how then ſay the <hi>Quakers,</hi> that there is no Reſurrection? And yet a Ring-leader among them hath no leſs proudly then ignorantly given out, That <hi>if the complete happineſs of the Soul reſts in a re-union to a carnal Body, for ſuch it is ſown, then muſt we never cry out upon the Turks Alcoran; for ſuch a Heaven and the joys of it ſuit admirably well with ſuch a Reſurrection.</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Penn</hi>'s Reaſon againſt Railing, <hi>Pag.</hi> 138.</note> But this is evidently neither more nor leſs than to ſet up a piece of foppery of his own, that he may have the pleaſure and credit of beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it down; for certainly never any Chriſtian affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the Body ſhould be raiſed to a life of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, that revelling and junketting were the joys of Heaven. But <hi>this</hi> all that pretend to any love and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97998:7"/>honour for the Goſpel, have unanimouſly agreed upon, that at the Reſurrection the Body ſhall be the ſame as to its ſubſtance, but very different as to its qualities; <hi>it is ſown in corruption, it is raiſed in incorruption; it is ſown a natural body, it is raiſed a ſpiritual body.</hi> But it is unconceivable by this profound Logician, how a thing ſhould be the ſame, and yet notwithſtanding that be changed; as if there were any the leaſt abſurdity in ſaying, that a Man might be the ſame and not the ſame in divers reſpects; may he not be changed from weak to ſtrong, from proud to humble, from ſickly to healthful, and yet be ſtill the ſame Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? When the <hi>Jews</hi> ſaw the Man, out of whom the Devils were caſt, ſitting at Jeſus Feet, cloath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in his right mind, they made no doubt, notwithſtanding this wonderful change that had been wrought in him, but that he was the ſame Man that was poſſeſſed before. I have not inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo long upon this Objection, for any ſtrength that I perceived in it, but for the ſake of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle itſelf, which is the powerfulleſt motive to a good life, as all People muſt own, that will not take upon them to be wiſer than God: So that to deny the Reſurrection, is to cut the very Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news of Piety, and caſt a worſer ſhade than that of Death upon the Primitive Martyrs; who, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs would never have endured their ſharp afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97998:8"/>with that unimitable courage and conſtancy; if it had not been for the joy that was ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, nor born thoſe marks of the Lord Jeſus in their Bodies, if they had not looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſcars of their ſtripes and hurts, as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſigns that they belonged to Chriſt, and that in due time he would ſeize upon them as his own peculiar. So the Author to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly, that ſome were tortured, not accepting de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, that they might obtain a better Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. But nothing but the certainty that this Article hath been denied, could make one think it poſſible that it ſhould, ſince it is ſo directly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to ſeveral Paſſages in Scripture, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly to the ſecond Verſe of the Twelfth Chapter of Daniel, <hi>Many of them that ſleep in the duſt of the earth ſhall awake, ſome to everlaſting life, and ſome to ſhame and everlaſting contempt;</hi> and ſo likewiſe to that Paſſage in St. <hi>John</hi>'s Goſpel, Chap. 5. <hi>The hour is coming, in the which all that are in the graves ſhall hear his voice, and ſhall come forth, they that have done good unto the reſurrection of life, and they that have done evil unto the reſurrection of damnation.</hi> Now certainly when the Prophet ſpeaks of them that ſleep in the duſt of the Earth, and the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt of them that are in the Graves, neither of them thought of the Souls being in that condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and therefore if any thing be waked out of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97998:8"/>ſleep, or come forth of the Grave, it muſt be the Body; which is ſo clear, that I defye theſe Sectaries with all their little ſhifts, and baſe arts of corrupting Scripture, to evade the force of theſe Texts, and uſe them as they have done ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>i. e.</hi> make them vaniſh into the Clouds and thick darkneſs of unintelligible allegories. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he be that profeſſeth any reverence for the Scripture, and yet doubts of the Reſurrection, all that I would deſire of him is to peruſe the Fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians,</hi> with ſeriouſneſs and impartiality, and then let him ſpeak his mind. It is moſt certain at Chriſt's ſecond Advent, <hi>when he ſhall judge the World in righteouſneſs, and miniſter true judgment unto all People,</hi> there will be a re-union of Soul and Body; and then fiery indignation ſhall be poured out upon the Adverſaries, but Mercy and Loving<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindneſs upon all thoſe that <hi>have kept the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and the Faith of Jeſus,</hi> Rev. 14.12. St. <hi>John</hi> tells us, <hi>that he heard a voice from Heaven, ſaying, write from henceforth, bleſſed are the dead, which dye in the Lord, for they reſt from their labours;</hi> are unmoleſted with the impertinence and malice, the folly and hypocriſie, the rage and perfidiouſneſs of buſie, falſe, and vexatious Mortals; but this is by far the leaſt part of their felicity; for after a ſhort ſleep in their Graves, they ſhall awake up
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97998:9"/>to Glory, and always have ſuch a tranſcendently delightful object in their view, as ſhall never ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer them to ſhut their Eyes againſt it; be as the Angels in Heaven, not only ready to execute God's Commands, but enjoying them too. But as for the unbelieving and impenitent Wretch, I have no glad tidings to tell him; for all his falſe hopes were built upon the Sands. And he, who would have been the rock of his Salvation, ſhall then put on only the <hi>deafneſs and hardneſs</hi> of the rock; not be moved to the leaſt pity by the moſt hideous and diſmal out-cries; but for ever remain inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to all complaints and intreaties. We are told indeed in Scripture, that God juſtifieth the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly; but that Paſſage muſt be underſtood, <hi>in ſenſu diviſo,</hi> of ſuch as were Ungodly, and not of ſuch as continue in ill-doing; for God cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare him to be juſt and righteous, who is unjuſt and unrighteous, without impeaching his own Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Righteouſneſs. It is as certain that grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Sinners, without amendment of life, ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be received into God's favour, as it is that by their reformation and renewing of their minds, they ſhall be adopted into the family of his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Children. Would God puniſh the imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sin ſo ſeverely in his innocent and <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Son, in whom he was well pleaſed,</hi> and will he pardon the unrepented Iniquities of a ſtubborn
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97998:9"/>Enemy? If he would not ſpare him that was in his Boſom, but pour out his moſt precious Blood, doubtleſs he will not ſpare the refractory after ſuch a dreadful and amazing Execution. Eternal Life is the gift of God, not to be purchaſed as a due reward of the moſt holy Converſation: But Death is the proper Wages of Sin, that which of right belongs to it, and without Repentance ſhall be fully pay'd. So that to imagine that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains an affection to one that will not part with his Iniquity and his Ruin, is to lay to his charge an unjuſt Sentence, and, as a neceſſary conſequent thereto, an undue Execution of it. Let us not therefore pleaſe our ſelves with the vain deluſions of being God's ſpecial Favourites, when our hearts are not right towards him; for doubtleſs only thoſe that live <hi>to</hi> him here, ſhall live <hi>with</hi> him hereafter. Give me leave to make ſome Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of what hath been delivered to the preſent occaſion, and I ſhall conclude.</p>
            <p>I do not pretend to have given you here a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of all the falſe Doctrines of <hi>Quakers,</hi> which are as much too numerous to be recited, as they are too foul to be owned. What I have concerned my ſelf with, have been only ſuch as have come in my way, and could not fairly be avoided. And thoſe I look upon as ſufficient to vindicate their prudence and honeſty, who have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97998:10"/>forſaken them and their Errors, and have come out from among them, that they might not be partakers of their Sins. And I hope that thoſe who have thus deliberately choſen to <hi>walk together with us, in the Houſe of God as Friends,</hi> will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bring any ſcandal upon our Profeſſion, whilſt they own it, nor upon themſelves by forſaking it; will never hearken to any Sophiſtry, that either the Tempter himſelf, or any of his Agents ſhall make uſe of for the ſeducing them back again, to thoſe Principles and Practiſes, which they have ſo wiſely and ſo ſolemnly renounced. <hi>For it had been better for them not to have known the way of righteouſneſs, then after they have known it, to turn from the holy Commandment dilivered unto them.</hi> For a relapſe, as it is more dangerous; ſo, when it may be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented it is more culpable too, then the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of a diſeaſe. <hi>But I am perſwaded better things of them that hear me now, and things that accompany Salvation, though I thus ſpeak.</hi> And to the end that you and they may be rooted and grounded in the true faith of our Church, I ſhall briefly ſhew you her temper, <hi>i. e.</hi> draw ſome of the great lines, by which ſhe may be known; for I have neither time, nor ability to repreſent her at large, and give you a full view of all her excellencies. In the firſt place then, <hi>She</hi> Accounts no Doctrine neceſſary to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but what is either expreſly founded upon, or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97998:10"/>by direct conſequence deduced from Scripture, <hi>which is the Pillar and ground of Truth,</hi> to which, with all the Saints that are, and have been, upon earth, <hi>and ſuch as excell in Virtue,</hi> ſhe pays a moſt profound Veneration; and takes it, as David did, <hi>for a Lanthern to her feet, and a light unto her Path.</hi> So very different is her treatment of it from that of <hi>Quakers,</hi> who vilify it as a thing of nought, and therefore in a ſtyle as peculiar to them as their behaviour, diſhonour it with the contemptuous Names of, Duſt, Death, and Serpents Meat,<note n="(C)" place="margin">
                  <hi>G. Fox</hi>'s News out of the North <hi>Pa. 14.</hi>
               </note> And it is plain they are not converſant in it; For then would they ceaſe to talk and act ſo fooliſhly and ſo wickedly as they do. It being one of the great excellencies of ſacred Writ, <hi>to give wiſdom und underſtanding unto the ſimple. She</hi> doth indeed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt upon the two Sacraments, of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi> And very good reaſon ſhe hath for ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, becauſe they are of Divine Inſtitution. The former was eſtabliſhed by our Saviour, when he gave his Diſciples a Commiſſion to <hi>go and baptize all Nations in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And when he hath enacted it as a law, That all his followers ſhall be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into his Church by that laver of Regeneration, <hi>can any one forbid them Water that they ſhould not be baptized?</hi> And as for that other Sacrament of the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97998:11"/>Lords Supper, certainly it muſt be a ſtrange Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of oppoſition that poſſeſſeth them who gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay it, for can there be any thing more endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than our Lords appointing that perpetual feaſt, except it be the love that made him do ſo? Is his precious Blood-ſhedding become ſo vile in our Eyes, that we cannot bear the remembrance of it? And yet neither the benefit nor the ſacredneſs of the Inſtitution, could reſtrain a Blaſphemous <hi>Quaker</hi> from this unſufferably vile Reflection upon it, Their Communion Bread and Wine, is the Table of Devils, and Cup of Devils,<note n="(D)" place="margin">
                  <hi>G. Foxe</hi>'s News out of the North, <hi>Pa. 14.</hi>
               </note> And yet ſome of the inferiours of this wicked Crew, have payed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Honours to this vile Wretch, and <hi>W. Pen</hi> hath ſince vindicated them:<note n="(D)" place="margin">
                  <hi>W Pen.</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das and the Jews <hi>Pa. 44.</hi>
               </note> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly St. <hi>Paul</hi> took it for granted, that his <hi>Corinthians</hi> neither would, nor ſhould abſtain from it, when he only directed them how to prepare themſelves for it, <hi>Let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that bread and drink of that Cup,</hi> 1. Cor. 11.28. And if this be not a ſtanding Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, never to be let fall, certainly the Apoſtle would not have recommended it to us by ſuch an enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging account as he hath given us, at <hi>V.</hi> 26. of the fore-mentioned Chapter, <hi>as often as ye eat this Bread, and drink this Cup, ye do ſhew, or ſhew ye, the Lords Death till he come,</hi> till the end of all things,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97998:11"/>when the whole World ſhall be diſſolved, and this beautiful Frame of the Univerſe be firſt reduced to Aſhes, and then to nothing.</p>
            <p>Nor is <hi>She</hi> more intent upon purity of Doctrine, than that of Life; and therefore requires Holineſs in all her Profeſſors; ſo that if any of them are wicked Livers, they are not ſo by her Indulgence, but their own depraved inclinations. Their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godlineſs therefore can be no juſt imputation to her, the ſtrictneſs of whoſe rules is a ſufficient proof of her love of Virtue, and hatred of Vice. I own indeed that ſhe requireth a conformity to a few innocent Ceremonies; not that ſhe looketh up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them as abſolutely neceſſary, but only as fit to be obſerved for the ſake of good Order, Decency, and Edification; which is the ſole cauſe of her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning them. And to lay them aſide, would be of more miſchievous conſequence than ſome of their oppugners apprehend, or perhaps would conſent to, if they did; for they ſeem to me to have the ſame kind of uſefulneſs that leaves have, which if they be not too numerous, are both an Ornament to the Tree, and a Fence to the Fruit. And now that I may not be ſuſpected to have any By-end in what I have delivered, as if I had not ſpoken the very Thoughts of my Heart, I do with all imaginable Sincerity make this Wiſh, may my Portion in the next World be with thoſe that are true Members
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97998:12"/>of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who walk worthy of that their Profeſſion; may I have the Reward which God in his Mercy, for his dear Son's Sake, ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow upon them, whoſe Faith and Practiſe are agreeable to her Doctrines and Rules. What now remains, but that we preſent our humble Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions at the Throne of Grace, in behalf of this good-natured, this Orthodox, and Uncorrupt Church; that God would continue to be <hi>her Guide and Defence;</hi> that he would keep and ſtrengthen in the true Faith and Holineſs of Life, all the Members of her Communion, and daily add to her ſuch as ſhall by his Bleſſing ſave both themſelves and others: <hi>Which God of his infinite mercy grant for Jeſus Chriſt's ſake, to whom be rendred as is moſt due, all Honour, Glory, Praiſe, Might, Majeſty and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, both now and for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="oration">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:97998:12"/>
            <head>Dr. <hi>John Spire</hi>'s ORATION, AT THE <hi>Pariſh-Church of St.</hi> OLAVE-SOUTHWARK.</head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <date>September the <hi>8th.</hi> 1700.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>It is probable it may ſeem ſomewhat ſtrange to many for me to appear after this manner in this Place; but let it not be accounted either preſumption or rudeneſs in me ſo to do, for my undertaking is juſtifiable in the ſight of God and all good Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FOraſmuch as upon the Occaſion of my being here the firſt time, which was on <hi>Trinity-Sunday,</hi> the <hi>26th.</hi> Day of <hi>May,</hi> 1700. and that cauſed a diſturbance in this Place, and for the prevention of the like again, as well as many, and various falſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97998:13"/>Reports that have been ſpread up and down, and that I have frequently met with all for ſo doing. I think it very proper to ſignifie ſomething of the Reaſon of my coming hither, and alſo to give you a short account of my Life down to this Day.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but many will be ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, why ſuch a Man and his Family or Friends come to Church, who have ſo many Years been Diſſenters from her; to which Queſtion I shall return one general anſwer by acquainting you as followeth.</p>
            <p>I was born of Honeſt Chriſtian Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents in the County of <hi>Berks,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 40 Years ſince Baptized accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the uſage of the Eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>England,</hi> and Educated therein till I was about 13 Years of Age, at which time my Parents Joyned with the People called <hi>Quakers;</hi> and afterwards
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97998:13"/>I was inſtructed in their way, in which I continued about 26 Years, and in the Year 1694, when thro' the good Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Almighty God, I began to have ſome ſmall glances of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, from which, with many others, I had ſo many Years ſwerved: upon this Diſcovery I published a ſmall thing in print, to vindicate my ſelf and my Friends, many of which are here preſent, from ſome erroneous <hi>Tenets</hi> held by the <hi>Quakers,</hi> for which I received ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great Abuſes from them, and was excommunicated (or diſowned) under the Hands of 24, from being of their Communion.</p>
            <p>And in the Year 1696, finding by many of their Books and Preachments, that they ſlighted the Humanity of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: I did in that Year print a ſmall Piece, aſſerting the Humanity of Chriſt from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97998:14"/>Scripture Teſtimony, for which Ialſo ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered many Reproaches, and have it now under a <hi>Quaker</hi> Preacher's Hand, baring date the 27 of <hi>June</hi> 1696 what affronts I then received, who after his long Scribble, thus violently utters him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf againſt me. He tells me, the Lord will confound me, that God will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy me; he calls me a Ravening Wolf, and bids me call in my Book that aſſerts the Humanity of Chriſt, and ſays withal, that the Lord requires it of me.</p>
            <p>In the Year 1698 it pleaſed God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to let me ſee that thoſe two great Ordinances of Chriſt, Baptiſm, and the Lord's Supper are thankfully to be received by all ſincere Chriſtians till his coming again at the laſt and great Day.</p>
            <p>And I do hereby freely acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my former Error, in denying the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97998:14"/>Benefit and Neceſſity of Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, as well as in ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the uſe of the Holy Scriptures, as alſo in Denying that great and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Article of the Reſurrection of the Dead, all which with many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of my Friends and Relations, I have been taught by the Principle Leaders, and Teachers of the aforeſaid People; and do own I was ſo far ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced as to help to teach and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage others in theſe abominable Errors, which ſin I truſt the Lord of his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy hath pardoned becauſe I did it Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly.</p>
            <p>I do alſo hereby freely declare, that I own for Subſtance the Doctrine of the 39 Articles of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and deſire that I may live and dye in that Faith, into which I was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized. What I have further to add is, that you and I may perſevere in the Way
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97998:15"/>and Worship of the true God, and that we may be exemplary one to the other, and Patterns of Humility, as becomes the Chriſtian Religion, that when Days and time shall be no more to us in this World, we may have our Dwelling and Habitation Eternally in the Heavens with the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>To whom with the Father and Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour and Glory, now and for ever.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>John Spire,</hi> Junior.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
